Finding Aid for Helen Gibson Cope collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen Gibson Cope Collection 1867-1987
Cope, Helen Gibson, collector
1.0 linear foot (in 2 boxes) and 1 outsize folder
2013142 Aa 2 AUl
Collection of papers related to Jones-McDonald-Gibson-Cope families of Macomb County, Michigan. Genealogical chart, marriage certificate, high school diploma, photographic scrapbook, family correspondence and two different drafts of a compiled history for James Jones and his family descendants, spanning the years 1867 -- 1987. This collection is related to the James Henry McDonald family collection, which is also held at Bentley Historical Library.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Materials received from Ann McDonald Barber, M.D. (donor no. 10953 ) in July 2013.
No further additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
James Jones, born June 29, 1804 in England, immigrated to America in 1832, where he met and married his wife, Elizabeth Funnell, that same year. The family moved to Meade, Michigan, in Macomb County, in 1834. Jones owned 500 acres of property in Michigan and served as the Justice of the Peace in Macomb County from 1862-1866, and again in 1870.
James Jones' daughter, Elizabeth Ann, married Theodore McDonald in 1852 and re-located from Meade to Ann Arbor, Michigan. Elizabeth and Theodore attended University of Michigan and ran a grocery store on Forest Avenue for 45 years. They had four children together whom they raised in Ann Arbor.
One of their daughters, Ann Elizabeth, married Edward B. Gibson in 1887. Ann's brother, James H. McDonald, compiled the family's first genealogical history in 1910, "James Jones Family Record -- Macomb County, Michigan." This record was updated and expanded upon by Ann and Edward's daughter, Helen Gibson Cope, in the 1950s. Helen's account of James Jones' family descendants was revised most recently in 1987 by her nephew Jim Gibson.
The collection contains photographs, genealogical research, a scrapbook, correspondence and memorabilia of James Jones and his family descendants, including Ann Elizabeth McDonald and Helen Gibson Cope, from whom much of this collection originates. Materials span the years 1867-1987, with a genealogical chart created in 1954 and also many undated family photographs. The material is organized into two boxes and the genealogical chart is housed in an outsize folder.
Subjects:
Cope, Helen Gibson.; Gibson family.; Jones family.; McDonald family.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Genealogy.; Macomb County (Mich.)--Genealogy.
Genre Terms:
Diplomas.; Genealogical tables.; Marriage certificates.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.
- Helen Gibson Cope collection, 1867-1987
  - University of Michigan Commencement Book, 1930 (Box 1)
  - James Jones Family Record, 1804-, Meade, Michigan, booklet 1940s (Box 1)
  - James Jones Family of Meade, Michigan, 1804-1987, booklet by H. G. Cope, updated 1987 (Box 1)
  - James Jones family genealogical research and correspondence (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1)
  - McDonald and Gibson family portraits 1867-1905 and undated (Box 1)
  - Deborah M. Gibson photos, 1920, 1927 and undated (Box 1)
  - McDonald-Gibson family photo album, undated (Box 2)
  - Helen Gibson Cope scrapbook, 1912-1919 and undated (Box 2)
  - Framed photograph of Ann Elizabeth Gibson's parents, undated (Box 2)
  - Ann Elizabeth McDonald high school diploma, 1873 (Box 2)
  - Ann Elizabeth McDonald marriage certificate, 1887 (Box 2)
  - Helen Gibson, 1908 junior class photograph, Ann Arbor High (Box 2)
  - School (Box 2)
  - Undated photograph (Box 2)
  - James and Elizabeth Funnell Jones Family, genealogical chart, by H.G. Cope and drawn by E.T. Cope, 1954 (Folder 1)
Related collections
McDonald family papers, 1783-1938.
James Henry McDonald photograph collection.
Ogden Jewell scrapbook, 1893-1896.
Class of 1876 (University of Michigan) records.
Mary Alice Williams papers, 1871-1891.
Sarah Drake Smith Fors collection, 1871-2000 (scattered).